...what has turned into a
classic Formula 1 season.
...with the weather
conditions so uncertain,
the drivers prepare for...
...the track is still
dangerously wet,
but following a drivers meeting,
a decision has been taken.
Three minutes to go.
Everybody off the grid now.
25 drivers start every
season in Formula 1,
and each year, two of us die.
What kind of person
does a job like this?
Not normal men, for sure.
Rebels,
lunatics,
dreamers.
People who are desperate
to make a Mark
and are prepared to die trying.
My name is Niki Lauda,
and racing people know
me for two things.
The first is my
rivalry with him.
What about Hunt? Has he changed?
No, he's going on wets.
I don't know why it
became such a big thing.
We were just drivers busting
each other's balls.
To me this is perfectly normal,
but other people saw
it differently,
that whatever it was
between us went deeper.
The other thing I'm
remembered for
is what happened on
1st August 1976,
when I was chasing
him like an asshole.
Yeah, that's the one. On the
second shelf. Thank you.
Trauma trolley, please.
I think the racetrack telephoned
ahead that I was coming.
Hunt. James Hunt.
What's the matter? No one ever
seen a spot of blood before?
- Are you all right?
- Absolutely fine.
We all thought you'd
been in an accident.
I have.
If you call a
friendly disagreement
with another driver an accident.
What did you disagree about?
It's none of your business.
Sorry.
His wife.
That's going to need a
couple of stitches.
- It's a nasty cut.
- It was a nasty blow.
Done with a bloody crowbar.
- Why? What did you do?
- Nothing.
Only what she asked me to do.
Which was...?
I'd be happy to show
you if you like.
Sorry.
I have a theory why women
like racing drivers.
It's not because they
respect what we do,
driving round and
round in circles.
Mostly they think
that's pathetic
and they're probably right.
It's our closeness to death.
The closer you are to death,
the more alive you feel.
The more alive you are. And
they can see that in you.
They feel that in you.
My name is James Hunt.
My father is a stockbroker,
my sister is a barrister
and my brother is an accountant.
And I,
well, I do this.
It's a wonderful way to live.
It's the only way to drive.
As if each day is your last.
I've never been to a
Grand Prix before.
You still haven't.
- This is Formula 3.
- What's that?
That's a lower division,
where idiots like me mess about
in the hop of being
talent-spotted to race in F1.
- You look disappointed.
- No.
You only slept with me because
you thought I was famous.
That's not true!
Don't worry. I will be one day.
Morning, everyone.
- This is Nursie.
- Gemma.
Nursie, this is Bubbles
Horsely, team manager.
How do you do?
- Bubbles?
- Yeah.
Doc Postlethwaite, our designer.
How do you do?
And Alexander, Lord
Hesketh, the team's owner.
How do you do?
Fine, thanks.
Well done, Superstar!
- That's the car?
- Yep, that's her.
Lotus 59.
1000cc. Cosworth Mae engine.
She's no beauty, but
goes like the slappers.
Nothing to be worried about.
Does it before every race.
Good sign, actually.
Means he's stoked.
All Formula 3 cars to
the assembly area.
Now, please.
...drivers please bring them
to the scrutineering bay now.
All right, Superstar?
Never better, patron.
- Have a gargle with this.
- Thank you.
Quick toke of this.
At Crystal Palace today,
James Hunt's on pole,
with Austrian newcomer
Niki Lauda alongside him
and Dave Walker
completing Row 1.
Row 2 is Mike Beuttler
and Dave Morgan,
with Tony Trimmer
and Gerry Birrell.
Who's that?
He's new.
- Some German.
- Austrian.
He's been here since 5 a.m.
walking the track.
You might actually have to
concentrate today, James.
You'll need these.
Okay, start her up.
Ah! What music!
They could never
have imagined it,
those pioneers who
invented the automobile,
that it would possess
us like this,
in our imaginations, our dreams.
Nursie, men love women,
but even more than that,
men love cars!
- Come on, James!
- It's James! Go on, James!
Go, James!
Hunt's still in the lead,
but Niki Lauda is
right on his tail!
Hunt and Lauda are proving to
be in a class of their own.
They're leaving the
pack far behind.
Herr Red Devil's on his tail.
Lauda takes a look
down the inside...
...and he's sold him a dummy!
Lauda is through!
He's in the lead!
Hunt will be determined to
make up for that mistake.
Hunt's in Lauda's slipstream.
Lauda's not leaving any gap.
The Lotus goes for the inside.
It's an aggressive
move from Hunt.
There's contact!
The leaders have spun out!
Lauda's facing the wrong way!
The back marker's gone through!
You can see why Hunter's
fellow drivers call him.
"Hunt the Shunt."
Asshole!
- Go on, James!
- The Kraut's out of it!
Lauda is clearly furious.
There's every reason to expect
sharp words in the pit.
It's going to be
victory for Hunt.
It's going to be an ignominious
defeat for Niki Lauda.
So James Hunt scores his
third major Formula 3 win
of the season here,
at Crystal Palace,
after a desperate
battle with Niki Lauda.
Lauda was unable so restart
after Hunt's aggressive move
caused them both to spin out
in the last lap of the race.
Hard luck. Better
luck next time.
Hey, asshole!
That was my line. I
had that corner.
You mean the one
that you spun out of
and finished facing
the other way?
I think that corner had you.
That move was total suicide.
What if I hadn't braked?
- We'd have crashed.
- But we didn't, did we?
Thanks to your impeccable
survival instincts.
Fuck you! What's your name?
James Simon Wallis Hunt.
Remember it, my
little Jerry friend.
- Jawohl! Remember ze name.
- It's very simple.
Hunt, it rhymes with cunt!
A word that happens to
describe you perfectly.
Who was that?
I've no idea. He looks
like a rat, doesn't he?
In my hometown, Vienna,
my family's famous
for one thing:
Business.
My grandfather was
a businessman,
my father, too.
So when they heard I wanted
to race cars for a living,
They are a few things to say.
Good.
So if my family wasn't
going to help me,
I decided to risk everything
and take out a Loan myself.
I found a Formula 1
team with an Ok car
and an owner who had
run out of money
and was willing to
accept my terms.
And so, ladies and gentlemen,
I'm delighted to say...
that the winner of the Guild
of Motoring Writers Award.
Driver of the Year...
is James Hunt.
Superb news!
- Well done, James.
- Superstar!
Fantastic!
- Well done.
- Thank you so much.
Yes!
My parents always wanted
me to be a doctor
or a stockbroker or something.
They gave me
the first-class education, but
that went all terribly wrong
and I ended up with you lot.
Thank you. I need it
more than you do.
I mean, I have a hot head,
an inability to
tolerate discipline...
- Yes!
- Very true!
I fall out with people
left and right.
The only creatures
I've ever really loved
or treated honorably
are budgerigars.
So in any normal area of
life, I'd be, or I am,
a total liability.
The only thing I've got going
for me is I'm quick in a car.
So thank you for this and
for acknowledging that.
I'm going to give
it to my father
and tell him to put
it on the mantelpiece
and imagine it's a first-class
degree in medicine.
Well done, Superstar.
Another season like that,
I'll move you up
to the big time.
Come on, you don't
think I'm ready now?
You are.
I'm not. I've got to
find you a car first.
Well, go on, then.
Chop chop. Don't wait too long.
You don't want him to
do what Lauda just did.
- Why? What did he do?
- Got himself a drive, with BRM.
How the hell did he do that?
He's a nobody.
He's never won a bloody thing.
Apparently, took out a
Loan and bought his way in
with two million
Austrian shillings.
Jesus.
Niki Lauda.
Here for pre-season testing.
BRM?
Sign the release form. I'll
let them know you're here.
- Mr. Stanley.
- Good morning.
- Clay!
Let me introduce you to
our number one driver.
Clay Regazzoni.
- How are you?
- Good.
Pleasure.
And these are your mechanics.
They're reporting
exclusively to you,
as per contract.
Pleasure.
- Do you wanna see the car')
- Sure.
Hello.
There she is. P160.
- Same as Regazzoni's?
- Identical in every detail.
How much does she weigh?
- 600 kilos.
- But that's crazy.
- Why so heavy?
- It's a V12 engine.
That lump weighs
190K on its own.
Okay.
What horsepower are you getting?
- No, no, 450.
- It's not enough.
It needs to be 500.
And the engine needs to be.
- We already tried.
- Tried what?
Everything
We replaced the entire
exhaust system.
- Barely made the difference.
- Are you using magnesium parts?
Now the engine block.
Any mounting or fixing
plates, strip it out also.
When you've done that,
we have to look at
the aerodynamics,
front and rear wing.
Okay, thank you. Good night.
What was Regazzoni's time?
1:53.
Okay, now put him in my car and
he'll go 2 seconds faster.
- Well, that's impossible.
- No chance.
We've been working
on it all night.
Put Regazzoni in the car.
See what happens.
I don't understand. Why
am I supposed to do this?
I don't know, Clay.
He wants you to
take it for a spin.
Gloves, please.
- I'd say we push it...
- All right.
What did you do to the car?
That's information
I'll share with you
under certain conditions only.
Go on.
A guaranteed place in the team.
And a paid contract
on equal terms
with Regazzoni for two years.
Are you crazy?
Clay's a senior figure in F1.
You're just a rookie!
The only reason we took you on
is because you're paying us.
Well, as of now, if
you want me to stay,
we rip up the contract,
I don't pay you a cent.
That's outrageous!
Was he quicker in my car?
He was, wasn't he?
Did he go two seconds faster?
Two point three.
So, have a think,
work out your priorities
and get back to me.
Hey, Niki.
I know what you're going to say,
that it's none of my business.
What?
If it's the track manager you're
taking on your date tonight.
It's none of your business.
Okay, but if you want my advice,
I'd let this one go.
I'm not questioning your taste.
She is a great girl, but...
Agnes' last boyfriend
was a British Formula 2 driver
who has a reputation
for two things,
for being a little
crazy on the track...
and for going all
night and all day
and all night again in bed.
He's a good driver,
but an immortal fuck apparently.
I don't know about you,
but that's not an act
I'd like to follow.
But if that doesn't
bother you...
What's his name, the driver?
Hunt. James Hunt.
You see, you share information
and I share information.
That's what teammates are for.
- Where the hell are we going?
- I promise it'll be worth it.
Just keep them closed.
Wait for it.
There.
What do you say?
She's Formula 1.
Yes, she is, Superstar.
Your brother and I got together
with the bean counters.
And since the economics
of F1 are not
so significantly different
to the economics of F2,
well, we thought if we were
going to be losing money,
we might as well be doing it on
the big roulette table in F1.
You fat, little, inbred beauty.
Come here.
Actually, credit where it's
due, we got the idea from Niki.
- Who?
- Lauda.
Bought his way in
rather than mess about
in the lower divisions.
I thought
"Bloody hell, he's right."
No sponsorship, Superstar.
I hope you approve.
No vulgar logos for
cigarettes or condoms.
Just plain white with the flags.
And racing overalls
which read
"Sex. Breakfast of champions."
So when do we start?
- Soon as you're ready.
- Ready?
I've been waiting for
this my whole life.
VILLAGE OF WATKINS GLEN
When the season started,
people wondered
whether Lord Hesketh
and his team
of upper-class enthusiasts
were bringing glamour
to the racing community
or just comedy.
Certainly it was the first
time anyone had seen
a Butler sewing oysters
and caviar in the pits.
But they have made
quite an impact.
6th in France, 4th in
Britain and 3rd in Holland.
All drivers on the track,
caution flags are out.
A severe crash at the Esses.
Red flag. There's a
car off the track.
And reports are reaching
me that there's been
a serious accident
in qualifying.
The identity of the driver
we don't currently have,
but as you can tell from
all the activity going on
towards the track, it was clearly
a grave incident indeed.
We will, of course, have more
information as we get it,
but it is the sight and sound
of F1 nobody likes to see.
- Get your hands off me!
- Hey, come on!
Drivers of top stature we've
lost just in the past 4 seasons
have included Piers Courage,
Jochen Rindt,
Jo Siffert,
Roger Williamson
and today, at Watkins Glen,
Formula 1 has claimed
another driver.
The Tyrrell team have
withdrawn from the race.
Their places on the grid
will be left empty.
- Terrible.
- They should cancel the race.
Why?
He made a mistake, went
into the corner too fast.
It's his fault.
- Is that right?
- It's obvious.
Look at the tyre marks.
So says the nobody, who had
to pay for his own drive.
How's that working out
for you, by the way?
Fine.
How is it at the back?
Not planning on being
there for long.
Ten minutes to the warm-up lap.
Ten minutes.
Arsehole.
Heading into the Grand Hotel
hairpin, second gear.
Turn in hard, looking
for late apex,
gentle with the bar.
Heading into Portier,
second gear,
clip the apex,
light brake, stay in second,
looking for a good exit.
Heading through the
tunnel, gradual right,
up through third,
fourth, fifth...
ls Alexander around?
Yes, he was.
He went back to the
house to take a call.
He'll be back shortly.
He only wanted to show
me his pride and Joy.
Rhymes with 'boy' if you ask me.
And 'toy.'
God, it's so flimsy.
For something that
costs so much.
There's no comfort, no
protection, nothing.
No, it's just a little
coffin, really.
Surrounded by high-octane
fuel in here.
Being driven round 170 mph.
To all intents and purposes,
this thing's a bomb on wheels.
You're James, aren't you?
Yes.
You fit the description.
Is that right?
Suzy. Friend of Alex's.
Yeah, yeah.
I know exactly.
What was the description?
Mostly positive in
terms of appearance.
Negative only in
terms of character.
I've been told to avoid you.
By whom?
Alexander.
He says you're a bad boy.
Alexander doesn't know
what he's talking about.
I was. I'm not anymore.
The new me is very professional.
Early to bed, early to rise.
All very dull,
but according to the team,
the best way to keep beating
the goose stepper.'
Is that what you were
doing when I came in?
Yes, visualization techniques,
memorising the circuit,
in this case Monaco,
which is up next.
Personally I've always
been a great believer
in getting there on the
day, putting my foot down
and playing chicken
with everyone else.
But they don't want me
doing that anymore.
They want my body like a Temple
and my mind like a monk.
And what about your
soul, your heart?
They've got ideas
about that, too.
They want me to stop
messing around,
settle down, get married with
the next nice girl I meet.
They think that'd
be good for me.
What do you think?
It sounds fucking awful.
But sine they're right
about most things,
they're probably right
about that too.
You don't fancy getting
married, do you?
Suzy.
JUST MARRIED
Hey, hey, hey!
- What's going on with him?
- Nothing. Nothing.
Didn't want to ruin your day.
It's...
- it's the Kraut.
- What about him?
He's just been
signed by Ferrari.
You're kidding me?
Jesus. How did that happen?
Did he buy his way in there too?
Well, the old man
took Regazzoni back
and he insisted
on it apparently.
He says that Niki's a
genius setting up the cars.
FERRARI TEST TRACK
FIORANO, ITALY
It's terrible.
Drives like a pig.
- You can't say that.
- Why not?
- It's a Ferrari!
- It's a shitbox!
It understeers like crazy
and the weight distribution
is a disaster.
It's amazing, all
these facilities
and you make a piece
of crap like this.
"Ferrari family,"
"our good friend
Clay Regazzoni."
You are family and friend
to the commendatore
as long as you win.
The minute you
don't, ciao, ciao.
I totally understand.
It's business.
I would do the same.
But it isn't just
business, is it?
What we do. It's passion, love.
Which is why we are prepared
to risk our lives for it.
Not me.
If I had more talent and
could earn better money
with something else, I would.
How do you know you
will make money here?
You haven't yet.
Not yet, but I will.
If you can, I can.
You know, are you
ever not an asshole?
- Why am I an asshole?
- Well...
By now I'm both quicker than you
and better at setting up a car.
You can't deal with it,
so you're the asshole.
Screw you.
I brought you along today
because you seem like
a lonely kind of guy.
I thought if I introduced
you to some nice people,
that could rub off on you.
Forget it.
Make your own friends.
Come on, Clay.
I'm sorry.
Are you leaving?
Yes.
Can you give me a lift
to the nearest town,
anywhere with a train station?
Sure.
Trento's half an hour's drive.
Get in.
What are you doing?
You hear that noise
when you accelerate?
- No.
- Your fan belt is loose.
My What?
And when you brake, your
foot goes all the way down,
which means there's
air in the system.
- Anything else?
- No.
Apart from the rear
brakes are worn out,
the front right
tyre is a bit soft,
which explains why
you're weaving so much.
How can you tell?
- My ass.
- Sorry?
God gave me an Ok mind,
but a really good ass which
can feel everything in a car.
You don't know what
you're talking about.
This car is fine. I just
had a service a week ago.
Not a good one.
Yes, a very good
one, very expensive.
This car's as good as new.
Relax.
- You're not in a hurry, are you?
- No.
As long as I'm back in
Maranello Monday morning.
Yes.
- Actually, we do, yeah.
- It's my honor, Niki.
- Thank you.
- My car is your car.
On one condition, though.
It's a piece of shit.
It's dog shit.
But if you drive it, you
make my life, Niki, eh?
Would someone please
tell me what's going on?
- Who are you? Should I know you?
- What, you don't know?
He's Niki Lauda,
Formula 1 driver,
and he just signed with Ferrari.
- Him?
- Yes.
- Impossible.
- Why?
Well, you know,
Formula 1 drivers,
they have long hair, are sexy...
their shins are open to here.
- Thank you.
- Yes.
Anyway, look at the way he's
driving, like an old man.
There's no need to drive fast.
It just increases the
percentage of risk.
We're not in a hurry.
I'm not being paid.
Right now, with zero
incentive or reward,
why would I drive fast?
Because I'm asking you to.
This is an incredible
battle between Niki Lauda
in the red Ferrari
and James Hunt
in the white Hesketh.
...the challenge
of Niki Lauda...
Lauda attacking Hunt. He
gets through on the inside.
Goes wide at the exit.
Hunt is past again.
Once more, Lauda tries
to sneak up the inside.
They're absolutely side
by side, wheel to wheel.
So evenly matched.
Fantastic battle between
these two great drivers.
Hunt is now ahead once more.
But Lauda's coming
back again now.
Lauda once more
sneaks up the inside.
And again he runs wide.
Again the Hesketh...
- Suzy, we're ready, come on.
- Just one second.
- Can we go, yeah?
- Okay, yeah.
We're in the closing laps of
this race at Watkins Glen.
They come down the hill.
And Hunt's got a problem!
Hunt pulls across to the left!
Lauda goes ahead on his own.
A sad end to a wonderful battle.
Hunt pushing off the marshal.
The chequered flag
is waiting for Lauda
and for Ferrari!
The title going to Niki Lauda,
who wins the race,
who wins the World Championship.
Do I look like a
racing driver now?
- Congratulations.
- Thank you.
Marlene.
With a car like that,
the rest of us
never stood a chance, did we?
Maybe the car being so good
has something to do with me.
Come on, Niki.
You're in a Ferrari.
I'm in a Hesketh.
Equal terms, the way
it was in Formula 3,
- Id' beat you and you know it.
- Never.
You might win one
race, maybe two,
because you're aggressive.
But in the long run, over
the course of a season,
no chance.
Right. Why is that?
Because to be a champion,
it takes more than
just being quick.
It's the whole picture.
You're just a charger
and a party guy.
That's why everybody likes you.
Try saying that and tell
me you're not jealous.
Why would I be jealous?
Think about it.
All that affection,
all those smiles,
is a sign of disrespect.
They don't fear you. Whereas
compared that to me.
Yes, compared to you,
whom no one likes.
- Right.
- Not even his own teammates.
Right. Because I'm
a serious guy.
I go to bed early, I look
after myself, after my car.
- Yes, you're very well-behaved.
- Go to work, kick ass.
And then, after the
race, I go home
instead of going to bars
and talk all this bullshit
with all these assholes.
Arseholes?
You should go home
more often too.
I heard you got married.
Yes, I did.
So where is she, this
mysterious wife?
In New York, working.
You know, I've never
seen you with her once.
No?
Well, maybe that's because
you're always at home,
on your own, looking
after yourself,
being a good little boy.
Take a drink on me, James.
Thank you, Niki. I
might just have two.
Right, Bubbles,
whatever it takes to beat
that prick next year,
just say it,
you're word is my command.
There are no lengths to
which I will not go.
And I mean it.
What the hell's going on?
Where is everybody?
What's the matter?
Do you know what the
date it is today?
Yes. It's November, the 14th.
Why?
Do you have any idea of the
significance of that date?
I don't know. Time to
start killing pheasants?
Actually, it's the deadline
for securing sponsorship
for the forthcoming
Formula 1 season.
Yes?
Which elapsed at
midnight last night
- and we didn't attract any.
- Well, so?
We aren't looking
for sponsorship.
Like you said, condoms an
cigarettes, vulgar, right?
Right.
Except we are, or were.
I've made something
of a miscalculation.
The economics, Formula
1, realities thereof.
It turns out not like the
lower divisions at all.
What are you saying?
I'm saying it's over, Superstar.
The banks have stepped in,
started laying everyone off.
Probably have to
sell this place.
On, Christ.
I need a drive, Pete. I need
you to find me a drive.
I mean, what about Lotus?
You don't wanna know.
- Actually, I do.
- Okay.
They felt your
reputation preceded you.
And what does that mean?
It's my other line. Look,
I'll get back to you.
Peter Hunt.
Fuck!
Don't worry. Something
will turn up.
Doubt that will help
in the meantime.
Why don't we go away
at the weekend?
Skiing.
Before I go back to New York.
Talk to me, James. Don't
make a stranger of me.
You know, Suzy, only a stranger
would invite me skiing
when they know I haven't
got a fucking drivel
I can't watch this.
What were you hoping for anyway?
A well-adjusted knight
in shining armour?
No danger of that.
- Let me give you some advice.
- I'm all ears.
Don't go to men who are
willing to kill themselves
driving in circles
looking for normality.
I never expected normality.
God knows I walked into
this with my eyes open.
I just hoped I'd married someone
who is half as impressive
on the inside as he
is on the outside!
At least there's something
behind the facade.
- James.
- Fuck off to New York, dear.
There must be a moisturiser
or an eye shadow somewhere
that needs your vapid
mush to flog it.
- Hello?
- Hi, James.
It's Peter. Something's
up at McLaren.
- What have you heard?
- Nothing. Why?
I heard Emerson's off.
He's dumped them in it.
Jesus. Get me in there, Pete.
Say anything, just
get me in that room.
I'll come straight to the point.
- Our esteemed lead driver...
- Fitti-fucking-paldi.
Has ditched us for another
team at the last minute.
- Coper-fucking-sucar.
- And we need a replacement.
Asa-fucking-P.
Fortunately a few hands
have already gone up,
good people.
- Jacky Ickx.
- I'm quicker than Jacky.
But he's consistent, dependable.
A grown-up.
Right, and will he go for that
gap when no one else will?
Will he put his life on the
line the day it really matters?
The sponsors like him.
What do you want, a driver
or a brush salesman?
- We wanna be successful.
- Yes, so do I.
But that means
beating Niki Lauda,
not being a show
pony for sponsors.
I heard about this
thing with Niki.
Everyone has.
You really thing
you can beat him?
I'd beat him in a McLaren.
It's the only car out there
as quick as the Ferrari.
Which is why I'm here, begging.
I'll do whatever you ask.
I'll put on a tie, I'll
smile for sponsors,
say the right things.
I can beat this guy, trust me.
Just give me the drive.
Yeah, he can be a loose canon.
And, yeah, he will
drive you all mad,
but in terms of raw
talent and right stuff,
there is no better
driver in the world.
He's the real thing, Teddy.
He's what we all
came into this for.
Nine days out of ten you'll
be pulling your hair out,
but on that tenth day
James will be unbeatable.
That is the day you will wish
you had him in your car.
You'll never win the
championship with Jacky Ickx.
You just might with James.
GRANDE PREMIO DO
BRAZIL INTERLAGOS
JANUARY 1976
and the Interlagos circuit
for the first race in the
1976 Formula 1 season,
where the main news is James
Hunt qualified fastest,
beating Niki Lauda's
Ferrari to pole position
by just 200th of a second.
New car.
- I noticed.
- Pole position.
I noticed that too.
Level playing field now,
my rally little friend.
Yeah.
Let's see where we
are after lap one.
Let's see where we are
in five races time.
Hunt has the pit
Lane pole position,
which should give
him the best chance
of outdragging Lauda's Ferrari.
If ever there was a doubt about
whether Lauda had a serious
challenger to this season,
Hunt and his McLaren have
certainly given us the answer.
BRAZIL LAUDA WINS
HUNT HAS ENGINE FAILURE
GRAND PRIX SOUTH AFRICA 76
Here in South Africa,
James Hunt is determined
to make amends after that
disastrous retirement in Brazil.
But it's Lauda who takes
the flag here at Kyalami.
James Hunt comes home second
to confirm his championship
challenge at last
and score his first
points of the season.
That wind you can feel is me
breathing down your neck.
Next time I'll have you.
We'll see in Spain.
SPAIN-HUNT WINS LAUDA 2ND
James Hunt finally takes his
first victory of the season
here in Spain, after
a brilliant drive.
It was only a matter of time.
- It's too wide.
- Disqualified.
- What?
- You're disqualified.
How can we be disqualified?
- 1.5 cm.
- It's the same car.
...McLaren M23 has proved
very controversial here.
Just make it narrower.
I don't care how.
New rear suspension.
New wishbones.
I wanna make sure this
thing is legal, no doubts.
Then we'd better move the oil
coolers to the old position.
- The wing brackets need...
- Fuck.
What the fuck d'you
think we're doing?
GRAND PRIX MONACO 76
And with Hunt disqualified
from his Spain win,
his championship here
is not going well.
And now it's all gone
wrong here at Monaco!
His engine is smoking!
Smoke pouring from the
engine of that McLaren!
And James Hunt is out!
Can you tell us what happened?
Sure. It's magic, we've
taken a great car,
a great piece of engineering
and overnight turned it
into a big, huge stinking turd.
BELGIUM MAY 1976
Shit!
What the hell have you done?
The car's evil!
It's fucking undriveable!
If there's a problem with
the car, we'll fix it.
The car is a piece of shit.
You should be appealing this.
- We are appealing.
- We'll son it out.
- They're killing us out there.
- Go an get your dick wet.
- You're a wanker!
- Fuck you!
You're fucking wanker!
But this was a good
race for you, no, Niki?
It's good for everyone
that the quickest car
happens to be a legal car.
James, your 50 points behind
Lauda in the championship.
You've had another
retirement today.
What's going wrong?
It's dirty politics
and dirty tricks,
that's what's going wrong.
So as we approach
the halfway point
in this year's Formula 1 season,
Ferrari and Niki Lauda
seem clearly on top
and James Hunt and
McLaren are struggling.
So, five races in,
how's it going so far?
It's fine. Just got a little
problem with an Austrian rat
and his team of Italian cheats
who've destroyed my car.
- What are you talking about?
- About the race in Spain I won.
Yeah, in a car which
is not legal.
Five eighths of
an inch too wide.
You know that doesn't have the
slightest effect on speed.
But you complained and
your team of lawyers
leaned on the authorities. Now
we've had to rebuild the car
- and it's become a monster.
- At least it's a legal monster.
You've had to
resort to cheating.
You're driving an illegal car and
call me a cheater? Pathetic.
- Rules are rules.
- Yes, and rats are rats.
Thank you. Thank you.
Do you really think
it upsets me, James,
calling me a rat because
I look like one?
I don't mind it.
Rats are ugly, sure,
and nobody like them,
but they're very intelligent
and they have a strong
survival instinct.
Wonderful.
No wonder she left him.
Anyone seen Suzy?
She's supposed to be here today.
We didn't wanna tell
you before the race.
Tell me what?
SUZY JOINS THE BURTON SHOW.
HUNT'S WIFE SEES ACTOR
AS LIZ FLIES TO MUM
Jesus.
Blonde model Suzy Hunt
stepped on to the dizzy
Elizabeth Taylor-Richard Burton
roundabout of romance yesterday.
Is that from him?
Yeah.
So when did all this start?
That weekend I went skiing.
Why have you come here, James?
I've got to get you back.
You don't want me back.
You never wanted to be
married in the first place.
- Yes, I did.
- Oh, come on, James.
You did it because you
hoped it might change you,
settle you down, help
with the racing.
No, I didn't.
And who knows, if it had
been just the drinking,
or the dope, or the
infidelity or the moods,
it might even have worked.
- But when it's all of them...
- Yes, I know, I'm terrible.
No, you're not terrible.
You're just who you are at
this point in your life.
God help anyone who wants more.
And Richard Burton,
will he be able
to give you more?
You know, he has quite the
bad boy reputation himself.
What's important is
how it feels to me,
and it feels like he adores me.
James!
Are you and Suzy
getting back together?
It's all very amicable.
My wife has found
herself a new backer...
I mean, lover, which
makes her happy.
And Mr. Burton has found a
way of feeling young again,
which makes him happy.
Let's hope his pockets are deep.
They'll need to be.
And I found a way to be
single and have an ex-wife
without it costing me a Penny,
which has to go down as the
biggest win of my career.
I have a flight to catch.
SUZY HUNT RACES
TO RICHARD BURTON
CIRCUIT PAUL RICARD
CHAMPIONNAT DU MONDE
We haven't seen this
sort of intensity
from James Hunt all season long.
Reports have been coming out
of the McLaren camp all week
that their car is now fully
legal and faster than ever.
FRANCE-HUNT WINS LAUDA RETIRES
Never mind the bloody wets.
We're still quick.
BRITISH GRAND PRIX
BRANDS HATCH SUNDAY
18TH JULY 1976
Hunt has really closed
the gap on Lauda
as they head into Druids.
Niki Lauda is under real
pressure from James Hunt
as they go up the hill
into Druids Corner.
And Hunt is in front of Lauda!
So James Hunt gets the
plaudits of the crowd,
the first Briton to win
a British Grand Prix
at Brands Hatch since
Jim Clark in 1964.
James, at the moment you've got
a terrific edge over the rest,
how have you achieved
this advantage?
Big balls.
Following an inquiry into
the disqualification
of driver James Hunt from
the Spanish Grand Prix,
it has been decided to
overturn this disqualification
and to restore his victory
and reinstate his points.
James!
A few weeks ago you were out
of the running completely
and now you're right back in it.
What's changed?
It's a combination of factors,
not all of which I'm
prepared to discuss here.
But justice being done re the
disqualification in Spain
helps and having my car
back at its best again.
Are you worried?
Welcome to the
This is a 14.2 mile track,
complete with 185
corners and bends.
the most dangerous circuit
on the season calendar.
In Formula 1 it is known
as "The Graveyard."
The weather conditions
are far from ideal
and latest reports indicate
there is no relief in sight.
Gentlemen.
Well, gentlemen,
please be quiet.
Thank you.
- Niki Lauda.
- Thank you.
I called this meeting because,
as all you drivers know,
stupid, barbaric, outdated
and dangerous track
in the world.
You've all seen the rain
that has been falling today.
Those of you with
experience know the ring
needs perfect conditions to
be even remotely acceptable
in terms of risk.
And today, with the rain,
it's anything but perfect,
so I called this meeting to
take vote to cancel the race.
Cancel the race?
There would be no
change to the situation
as far as points is concerned.
The race would
simply be cancelled.
This is bullshit!
If the race is cancelled,
none of us get our race fees.
That's true, you leave
without your fee,
but you might leave
with your life.
It also means that you
would effectively win
So I can see why this
suits you just fine.
Why?
There won't be no
points for me either.
No, but there'd be one race less
where I, or anyone else here,
- could catch you.
- James is right.
This is just tactics!
Maybe he's just frightened.
Which asshole said this?
Yes, of course, I'm frightened,
and so are you.
I accept every time
I get in my car
there's 20% chance I could
die, and I can live with it,
but not one percent more.
And today, with the
rain, the risk is more.
I suppose that all depends on
how good you are in the rain.
I have the track record here.
I'm the only person in history
to do the ring in under 7 Min.,
so, actually, it's to my
advantage to race here today.
Because I'm quicker
than all of you.
- Come on.
- Fine. Then let's race.
Yeah!
- Niki, let's race.
- Gentlemen, please.
Why are we here, Niki? Come on.
Well, all those in favor
of cancelling the race.
All those in favor of racing.
Gentlemen, the race is on.
- Ridiculous.
- What a waste of time.
You know, Niki,
every now and then
it helps if people like you.
In places the track is
still dangerously wet,
but following a drivers meeting,
a decision has been taken.
One minute to go.
Jochen's going on slicks.
You wanna change?
- Is Niki gonna change?
- No.
Then we stay on wets too.
- Niki, okay?
- I'm good.
All right, fire her up.
This season's fight for
the F1 World Championship
has so far been the
story of two men.
Thus far it's been going pretty
much the way of Niki Lauda.
But James Hunt has
qualified fastest here.
He is on pole position for
the German Grand Prix
with Niki Lauda alongside
in the blood-red Ferrari.
It's a long race.
If the track starts to dry out,
the wet-weather tyres will
no longer be as quick.
Niki Lauda and James Hunt,
side by side on the
front of the grid,
go away absolutely as one!
Lauda very aggressive
on Hunt there,
forcing the McLaren
onto the grass.
Lauda has the lead right now!
He leads into the first corner!
Hunt is in second place!
Mass storming past Hunt!
He made the right choice to go
with the dry-weather tyres.
Mass passing Lauda now!
Jochen Mass, in the number
12 McLaren, takes the lead!
Jochen Mass, the clear
leader, with everybody else
making the decision
to change tyres
after just one lap of this race.
Come on, let's go!
See? I told you to go on slicks.
You should've taken my advice.
Fuck off. Where's Niki?
Behind you. He made
the same mistake.
Come on!
Come on! What's going on?
The tyre-changing frenzy caused
a huge reshuffling of the pack,
- with Mass in the lead now.
- You're clear. Go!
Lauda urging his
mechanics to hurry.
It's a disaster! Come on!
What's going on, you assholes?
This race has gone
wrong for him so far.
His championship
rival, James Hunt,
is a long way up the road.
Lauda passing car after car.
He's just going past.
Mario Andretti's Lotus there.
Niki!
Get me out!
Help me!
Several cars are involved.
Looks like it might be
one of the Ferraris.
- Come this way!
- Come on, come on!
Keep trying
- Come this way.
- Okay.
The flood, which swept down Big
Thompson Canyon in Colorado,
was the worst since
records began.
In Formula 1 today, victory
celebrations were muted
after a horrific accident
involving world champion.
Niki Lauda.
Due to safety concerns
before the race,
the Austrian had said
he would not take pan,
but in the end he did.
He was making up for lost time
when he went off the track,
puncturing the
Ferrari's fuel tank.
Brett Lunger was unable to
avoid the flaming wreck
but was unhurt and joined other
drivers to rescue Lauda,
who was taken to Manheim
Hospital with severe burns,
the incident reminding us again
of the dangers of Formula 1.
Niki Lauda was trapped
for almost a minute
in a searing inferno
of 800-plus degrees.
James Hunt gains on the
absent Niki Lauda.
28th DAY IN HOSPITAL
29th August 1976.
- Morning, chaps.
- Hey, here's the man.
Looking good.
- What's going on?
- Jesus. It's Niki.
- What about him?
- He's here.
- What?
- He's racing.
Niki.
It's that bad, huh?
No.
In hospital, I asked them
straight, no bullshit,
how bad my appearance would be.
They said with time
it would be fine.
But it won't.
I can tell, seeing
your reaction.
I'll spend the rest of my life
with a face that
frightens people.
You know, Niki, I tried to write
you a letter at the time,
to apologise.
The drivers' meeting in
Germany, before the race.
- I swayed the room.
- Yes, you did.
That race should never
have gone ahead.
No, it shouldn't.
So in many ways I feel
responsible for what happened...
You were.
But, trust me,
watching you win those races,
while I was fighting
for my life...
you were equally responsible for
getting me back in the car.
- How are you feeling, Niki?
- Fine.
Niki,
can you confirm to us exactly
which procedures you had
and the expectations
for you recovery?
Sure.
I had a skin graft operation
where they put half my
right thigh in my face.
Now, it doesn't look too good,
but one unexpected advantage is
it's impossible to perspire
through a skin graft,
so sweat will never run
into my eyes again,
which is good for a driver.
When they heard about
your condition,
Ferrari immediately hired
a replacement driver,
Carlos Reutemann.
Yeah, before ever
reaching the hospital.
- Is Reutemann driving today too?
- Yes.
And keen to make an impression.
So let's see where
Mr. Reutemann finishes
and where I finish today.
James Hunt and McLaren
have caught up a lot
while you were away.
Yes.
So is there a question now
or are you just trying
to piss me off?
You still think you can win?
Yes, of course.
I have the better car.
And possibly I'm
the better driver.
But he's a clever guy and
he's used his time well
while I was lying
half-dead in hospital
to win some points.
And what did your wife say
when she saw your face?
She said, "Sweetie",
you don't need a face to drive.
You just need the right foot."
I'm being serious.
Do you really think your
marriage can survive
with the way you look now?
And I'm being serious too.
Fuck you.
Press conference over.
- That was hairy.
- You know how to get noticed.
I thought it went
well, to be honest.
They don't like it when
it's not going their way.
That's the game.
- See you.
- See you later.
- James, are you all right?
- Good, yeah.
I think I've got something for
you on that last question,
- About Niki.
- You heard about that?
James?
Please, James...
Now go home to your wife
and ask her how you look.
Prick.
So Niki Lauda, just 42 days
after his near-fatal
will race here today, at Monza
against all medical advice and
no doubt in incredible pain.
Photographers, please,
clear the grid.
Niki, it's time.
Okay?
Please, clear the grid.
One minute to go.
The returning Niki Lauda
seems overwhelmed.
He's been overtaken
by car after car.
Lauda's off line. He runs
wide onto the grass.
He wrestles it back
onto the track,
but that was a bad
moment for Niki.
Niki Lauda's the
reigning world champion,
but maybe in his current state
he's a danger out there,
to himself and to the
rest of the field.
And Stuck has collided with
Mario Andretti's Lotus!
Niki's boxed in! He's
got nowhere to go!
Niki Lauda's actually
making a move.
He's on Brambilla's tail.
He pulls out of the
slipstream to overtake.
Lauda's starting
to find the form
that early in this race
we believed he'd lost.
Lauda's now lapping
faster than Reutemann
and closing the gap ahead.
Lauda closing on
Carlos Reutemann,
the man called in to
be his replacement
And there's James
Hunt's McLaren,
smoking stationary by
the side of the road.
This is bad news for
Hunt's championship hopes.
It's Ronnie Peterson
who comes home the
winner here at Monza.
But all eyes are on the man who
finishes a brilliant fourth!
Niki Lauda!
What a race, what a
man, what a season.
With a 4th-place finish and
three priceless points,
Niki Lauda is a
major step closer
to retaining the
World Championship.
So the long, grueling and
incredibly dramatic season
comes down to this
final race in Japan,
in the shadow of Mount Fuji.
Niki Lauda goes into this
deciding race at Fuji
just three points
ahead of James Hunt,
Hunt knowing he must beat the
Austrian fair and square
to take the title.
James, do you think you can
cope with the pressure?
Well, I've never really
understood what that means.
I love my job. I love competing.
I love racing.
Maybe you should ask Niki.
He's the World Champion.
He's got everything to lose.
Mr. Lauda, are you
feeling pressure?
Do I look like I'm
I'm World Champion
and on the verge to become
World Champion again.
Hunt now has the
opportunity to win,
but it's not so easy
to become a champion.
You have to really believe
it to make it possible.
James, is there anything
you'd like to add?
If Niki is being tricky
and getting a kicky
out of playing mind games,
then fine, I'm flattered.
The fact is momentum is with me.
I've never felt better.
I fully expect the next press
conference we will have
will be with me as
World Champion.
Intermittent heavy
rain has been forecast
here at Fuji today,
along with strong winds
rolling in from the mountain.
And so with today's Japanese
Grand Prix to come,
Lauda's lead a
mere three points.
What a way to finish the season.
Hunt or Lauda?
The final chapter will unfold when
we bring you extended coverage...
They've got to cancel the race.
It's lethal out there.
The race is going ahead.
Television rights have been
sold all around the world.
The showdown between
you and Niki
is all anyone wants to see.
With heavy rain continuing
to fall here at Fuji,
a decision has
finally been made.
The 1976 Japanese Grand
Prix will go ahead.
All drivers to
your cars, please.
Five minutes to go.
- All right?
- All right.
- Hold still.
- What the hell are you doing?
To let the condensation out.
- It'll also let the water in.
- Not if you're leading.
Trust me, this race is
all about the start.
- Need a hand here?
- Yeah, hold it, Teddy.
Okay, start the bastard.
Good luck, kid.
Good luck, James!
30 seconds to go.
Electric tension here at Fuji.
80,000 bedraggled race fans
and the racing grudge
match of the decade.
And there's Mario Andretti
in pole position,
James Hunt alongside him.
On row two of the grid,
there is Niki Lauda,
and on row three of the grid, Joe
Schecketer from South Africa
in the six-wheel Tyrrell.
Behind him, the rest
of the 25-car field.
is underway!
In this conditions it
must be almost impossible
to drive a 450-horsepower car!
And it's Andretti
who has the lead,
but Hunt is attacking.
Hunt's going round the
outside of Andretti!
Niki Lauda following
him through!
Hunt leads into the
first right-hander!
Hunt comes through to complete
his first lap leading the field.
At least he has clear
vision in front of him.
Niki Lauda behind him,
eating his spray.
Lauda is slowing!
Niki Lauda is bringing the Ferrari no.
1 into the pit!
Some sort of problem,
we can't imagine what,
so early in the race.
What's wrong with the car?
Niki! What's wrong with the car?
Nothing. Car's perfect.
What are you doing?
I'm stopping
His mechanics are asking
what the problem is.
But wait! Niki Lauda's
getting out of the car!
This is sensational!
The reigning World
Champion, Niki Lauda,
is out of this race.
It's too dangerous.
Niki, you want me to say
there was a problem with
the car, for the media?
No.
Tell them the truth.
Now, what is happening?
They're talking to
the team manager.
Lauda explaining something.
With Lauda out, James Hunt
knows he has to finish
this race in third place or
higher to be World Champion.
But the job's not done
yet for James Hunt.
In these dreadful conditions,
he still has to go the distance.
Fifteen laps to go here at Fuji.
James Hunt or Niki Lauda?
This extraordinary
season is not over yet.
In this treacherous final
round, can James Hunt hang on?
And the scoreboard tells a story.
Lap 58.
Hunt in the lead.
Oh, God, his tyres,
they're blistering.
Brambilla very close behind him,
closing on him all the time.
And he's trying to drive
inside James Hunt.
Hunt cuts across the
orange March nose.
Hunt not having that at all.
And he's spinning.
He missed Hunt but almost took
James Hunt out of the race
and out of the world
championship.
Now we find Mario Andretti
closing on James Hunt.
Mario Andretti's
going past Hunt!
Hunt is slowing. James Hunt
seems to have a problem.
Despite this wet conditions,
these wet-weather tyres
wear extremely fast.
Hunt's tyres, they're gone.
Hunt nursing his car
back to the pit stop.
That back marker's
going past Hunt.
LAP 70 4 LAPS TO GO
Look at that left front tyre,
right front tyre, sorry.
No tread on it at all. And
the other one is flat.
Let's go! Let's go!
Okay? When did you
break your gear lever?
Nine or ten laps ago.
- Alistair, we need to lift it!
- Come on!
- At the front!
- Let's go!
Regazzoni's Ferrari and
Jacques Lafitte in the Ligier
have gone ahead.
Come on, hurry!
You did it. You're going
to be World Champion!
Not yet.
A few laps ago, James Hunt was
looking like champion elect.
Now it looks as though it's
all gone wrong for him.
- James.
- Come on!
- Listen.
- What?
Just go easy out there.
- What are you saying?
- I'm saying look after yourself.
We want you back in one piece.
You're too far back. There's too
many drivers in front of you.
- There's always next year.
- So that's it? It's over?
Clear!
James!
- Clear!
- Fuck it!
James Hunt rejoins the
race in sixth position.
There are four laps to go.
Surely no way back for the Brit.
Concentrate, Superstar.
Just brings it back
under control!
Sliding the McLaren on
the very edge there.
Hunt's M23 twitching this
way and that under braking.
And he almost loses
it right there.
Hunt on the tail
of Jacques Lafitte
in the blue Ligier.
Don't do it, James.
He's inches away
from the pit wall!
from the Ligier!
James Hunt has made
up another place,
but it's not enough and
this race is running out.
And Watson has spun!
Watson has spun!
Hunt manages to weave his
way between the back marker
and the stationary Penske.
He's catching Regazzoni,
but in these conditions,
it's one thing to catch up,
quite another to overtake.
He's alongside Clay Regazzoni!
This could be
the world championship!
He's got him!
Hunt crosses the line.
He needed to finish third
to score enough points
to be World Champion,
and in the confusion
here we're being told
that he may have finished 5th.
He finished fifth?
Our lap charts show
Hunt in third place.
Well, if the scoreboard's right,
it means he's just missed
out on the championship.
Crushing defeat for Hunt
after such a heroic drive.
I can see the race
stewards conferring,
examining the
official lap charts.
We're just going to have to
wait for their verdict here.
Let's get you out
of here, buddy.
I'm sorry, Teddy. I thought
I could make up the ground.
Sony? What are you talking about?
You did it!
- Did what?
- Jesus! You crazy bastard!
You came 3rd! You
got the points!
You're champion of the world!
James Hunt is now
officially confirmed
as finishing third
here in Japan,
and that means he is
champion of the world.
Our new World
Champion, James Hunt,
by just one single point.
Did we really win?
World bloody Champion!
- What are you going to do now?
- I shall be getting drunk.
It's wonderful, absolute dream.
And our special guest, Formula
1 champion, James Hunt.
JAMES HUNT WORLD CHAMPION
JAMES HUNT AGAINST ALL ODDS
Wait. Come on.
There's no better motor
oil than Havoline.
- Yes, me too. Where we going?
- Anywhere I want to go.
And I don't have to
hijack it, either.
As long as I pay for it.
I'm starving. Let's
get some food.
BOLOGNA, ITALY
- Where are you going?
- You lot go ahead.
I won't be a minute.
Niki!
Good to see you!
I heard you were spending
more and more time
- in one of these.
- Do you fly?
No.
- I don't think they'd insure me.
- You should try.
It's good for discipline.
You have to stay
within the rules,
stick to regulation,
suppress the ego.
It helps with the racing.
And there I was thinking you
were about to wax lyrical
- about the romance of flight.
- No, that's all bullshit.
So what brings you here?
A friend's wedding.
At least I think
it was a wedding.
Might have been a
birthday or something.
It's all a bit of a blur.
- Have you been at Fiorano?
- Pre-season testing.
- You're relentless.
- Thank you.
I'm not sure that was
meant as a compliment.
When do you start testing?
Next week?
No. What, are you nuts?
I didn't just win the
biggest thing of my life
so I could get right
back to work.
Why? You have to.
To prove to all the people
who will always say you
just won it because...
Because of what? Because
of your accident?
Niki, is that other
people or is that you?
I won, okay?
On the all-important day
when it came down to it,
we raced on equal terms,
equally good cars.
And I put my life on the
line and I saw it through.
- And you call that winning?
- Yes.
The risks were totally
unacceptable.
You were prepared to die.
- To me, that's losing.
- Yes, I was. I admit it.
I was prepared to die
to beat you that day.
And that's the effect
you have on me.
You'd pushed me that far.
And it felt great!
I mean, hell, isn't that
what we're in this for?
To stare death in the
face and to cheat it?
Come on, there's
nobility in that.
It's like being knights.
You English, you're
such assholes.
You know my position.
20% risk.
No, Niki, don't bring the
percentages into this.
Don't be a pro.
The minute you do that, you
kill what's good about this.
You kill the sport.
James!
I've got to go.
Careful in this thing.
James.
In hospital, the toughest part
of my treatment was the vacuum.
Pumping the shit
out of my lungs.
It was hell.
And while doing it, I was
watching television.
- You winning all my points.
- Your points?
"That bastard, Hunt," I'd say.
"I hate that guy."
And one day, the
doctor came and said,
"Mr. Lauda, may I offer
a piece of advice?"
"Stop thinking of it as a
curse to have been given
an enemy in life."
"It can be blessing too."
"A wise man gets more
from his enemies
than a fool from his friends."
And you know what? He was right.
Look at us.
We were both a pair
of kids when we met.
Hot-headed jerks in Formula 3.
Disowned by our families.
Headed nowhere.
And now we're both
champions of the world.
It was not bad.
No, it's not bad.
So don't let me down now.
I need you busting my balls.
- Get back to work.
- I will, Niki, I will.
But I intend to
enjoy myself first.
Some of life needs
to be for pleasure.
What's the point of having a
million cups, medals and planes
if you don't have any fun?
How is that winning?
- James!
- We're gonna leave without you!
James!
I'll see you on race day, champ.
You will...
champ.
You look good, Niki.
The only guy to have burnt his
face and it be an improvement.
Of course he didn't
listen to me.
For James, one world
title was enough.
He had proved what
he needed to prove,
to himself and anyone
who doubted him.
And two years later he retired.
When I saw him next in
London seven years later,
me as champion again,
him as broadcaster,
he was barefoot on a
bicycle, with a flat tyre.
Still living each
day like his last.
When I heard he'd died aged
45, of a heart attack,
I wasn't surprised.
I was just sad.
People always think
of us as rivals,
but he was among the
very few I liked
and even fewer that I respected.
He remains the only
person I envied.
Born3o.